Hello everyone
I am currently at a major tech company, serving as the head of AI search products.
Today, let's talk about the core competency model of an AI product manager.
First, to understand the core competency model of an AI product manager
Let's first take a look from the perspective of word formation
What is an AI Product Manager
So, an AI product manager
It can be broken down into two concepts: AI and product manager.
AI is actually the direction in our work
or the tools it utilizes in our work
some tools that are needed to be used
while product manager is our title
or the essence of this position
So how exactly should we understand these two aspects: direction and essence?
So AI represents the professional knowledge we need to master in our work
our applications
the products we develop
its scope of application
and what kind of R&D paradigm we should use
that is, the development method, to create our AI product
And the product manager defines the position of our work
defining the methods we need to use in our work
It also defines the roles and responsibilities we should undertake within the team.
So to better understand the core competencies of an AI product manager
then we need to focus on these two aspects
to focus on analyzing
So the first step is
Let's start with the product manager
When it comes to product managers
If we use the brainstorming method to break it down again
then it essentially breaks down into product and manager
namely the two concepts of product and manager
Now, the concept of a product
In fact, we encounter various types of products in our daily lives, right? Broadly speaking, we have hardware products and software products.
hardware products and software products
then our software products
including products like C-end and B-end products, and so on
the definition of a product
If we look at it from the textbook perspective
It would be a very dogmatic statement
For example, it refers to something that is used and consumed by people,
something that can satisfy people's certain needs, right
Broadly speaking
products can be physical products
could be a service
It could also refer to various types such as people.
In a narrow sense
Product specifically refers to internet products
It could be a service
It could be hardware
could be a service
Now let's take another look at this product.
this concept
It may still seem a bit too textbook-like.
particularly conceptual
Now let's take a look at
Yu Jun is a very famous product manager
a very famous product increment
He wrote a book called 'Yu Jun's Product Methodology,' in which he asks: what is a product?
He mentioned, what is a product?
Enterprises need to use products as a medium
to create user value and exchange value with users in this manner
Alright, then I'll draw a diagram below
We can see that a product is actually
is actually a medium for value exchange between enterprises and users
right
So what is the role of a product manager
is to create this medium
This user value may be fully met
meet a certain need of the users
And what is this commercial value
may be to pay for the company's products
subscribe
A good product manager
can make this value exchange smoother
more smoothly
more efficient
So this brings us to the question: what is a product manager?
Of course, if you shift your focus to actual job positions
or in the actual recruitment market
You will find that each company
the definition of a product manager varies across companies
The boundaries of their work vary.
For example, some companies might think it's okay
Product managers and product operations are separate, right?
You just need to focus on the product design features.
You don't need to handle operations
So in some companies, their responsibilities may
his role positioning may be
As a product manager, you need to oversee the design
You have to manage operations, right?
Some companies even go as far as to say, not only do you need to design features
You also need to design the style of the page
you also need to design user interactions, right?
the traditional division of labor in the UI or UE direction
are also incorporated into the boundaries of the product
Therefore, different companies
The definition of the product, or its boundaries, may vary.
However, if we focus on the role of a product manager
its core or this position
he is what we call a problem solver, right
He is a problem solver.
Then he needs to stand on the intersection of business and technology
considering from the perspective of user experience
responsible for the product's market outcomes
In other words, the core objective of a product manager
No matter what kind of product manager you are, right?
you are responsible for the outcome of this product
This is the most core definition of a product manager's role.
Of course, the product manager
It is also a rather broad concept
Product managers can also be classified into many categories, right?
For example, the most commonly heard one is, this product manager
your category, you can be a C-end product
You can also work on B-end products.
Of course, in the C-end, for example
say we individuals as consumers, right
consumer, this type of individual consumer, ToC products
which may be familiar to us
including WeChat that we use every day
this Taobao
Douyin, etc.
Similarly, for B-end products
perhaps we more often serve as a professional role
or a social role that is frequently used
like WeCom, right
and so on, some office software
Here, regarding the ToC to B concept
we won't go into excessive elaboration
What we need to understand is that
Even the concept of a product manager
there are also many categories
there are also many subdivisions
also includes many subdivisions
So, an AI product manager
It is within the category of product managers, it is a type, it is one type within the classification of product managers. 'The differences among product managers mainly lie in their respective industries, companies or departments, focus of work, and skill requirements, etc.'
Therefore, the AI product manager
"The differences among product managers mainly lie in the foundational aspects of product management," "The differences among product managers primarily depend on their understanding of the business, the focus of their role, and skill requirements," "The differences among product managers are largely centered on the foundational aspects of product management."
requiring us to master a niche area
and the core competencies involved
The differences among product managers mainly lie in their hands, and then we will proceed to see, so let's continue to look at the concept of an AI product manager
what exactly is the definition
So the core model of an AI product manager
Its core competency model actually consists of three aspects.
If we look at the overall market trend
So the emergence of market demand for AI product managers
actually emerged during this wave of large model development
emerged, right
It was born around the end of 2022 or the beginning of 2023.
So we know that this
the emergence of these large models
It is actually a significant technological breakthrough.
So we say technological breakthroughs are essentially a form of leapfrogging
that is to say, technical capability
It's likely to be, well, quite uneventful for a period of time, and then suddenly there's a moment
a new technology that suddenly emerges
causing the entire market demand to explode
So from this, we can see
technology and what it represents, the market demand it drives
is actually a leapfrog rise
This is the demand side of the entire market.
Now if we look at the supply side of the market
The supply side of the market is essentially talent, right?
Then, from the supply side of the market, the talent
The supply of talent has a notable characteristic
its fluctuation is actually relatively slow
because, whether it's the accumulation of human experience
or, for example, this school trains students, right
whether it's schools cultivating students
or say OK
We transition from other industries to become AI practitioners
his accumulation, his accumulation of experience
are highly correlated with time
You can't expect the market to suddenly, right?
suddenly emerge 1 million highly skilled AI professionals, this
competitors with particularly strong AI skills
This is totally unrealistic
Therefore, the talent supply in the entire AI market
it is actually a slow growth trend
At least in the past few years, this has been the case.
So, we are currently in a very obvious
in such a market cycle
it is essentially a highly explosive demand
and a slowly and steadily growing market supply, leading to such a supply-demand contradiction between them
such a supply-demand contradiction has emerged
then this supply-demand imbalance
or this gap in talent supply
In the past two years, it was more concentrated in some technical positions.
such as AI algorithms
or engineering
In recent years,
From 2024 to the present,
the entire supply gap is starting to shift, meaning the overall demand
began to spread to non-technical positions
So what are the non-technical positions
actually includes what we commonly refer to as products
operations, design, and other positions
So right now is actually a great time to transition into becoming an AI product manager.
such a time point
This naturally leads us to a core reflection on product managers
right
what kind of abilities do I actually need to possess
Or what methods I need to master
or what the market expects of me to become an AI product manager
what exactly is the demand
This is precisely the core content we aim to address today.
the core competency model of an AI product manager
As we can see across the entire market
it actually targets AI product managers
There are three major directions for its core competency requirements.
The first major direction is called the job skills of a product manager.
The second direction is called the understanding and application of AI technology.
The third direction is called the accumulation and insight of business scenarios
Now let's introduce them one by one based on these three core competency dimensions.
what preparations do we really need to make
First, let's look at the first path.
Product manager's job skills
In other words, the first step to becoming an AI product manager
In fact, our first step is to become a qualified product manager.
As we mentioned earlier, right
The basic concepts and fundamental definitions of a product manager do exist.
the AI product manager
is actually a specialized subfield within product management
So, if you want to become a good AI product manager
Then of course, you first need to become a good product manager.
So what exactly are the job skills of a product manager?
We know that the product manager
it is actually a position, right
Since it is a position
In this team, he must have his job responsibilities.
For example, as we just mentioned, one is a product manager
he is responsible for the overall outcome of the product
Since this position has its corresponding responsibilities
then there must be corresponding skills to fulfill these responsibilities
the corresponding job skills
right, the corresponding skills
These skills are referred to as the core competencies for this position.
Therefore, the job skills of a product manager
refers to what we need to excel as a product manager
What core skills do we need to master
So from this traditional perspective,
We can see that, as a product manager
He actually has an inherent competency model.
But in this traditional perspective, it actually refers to, okay
before the advent of AI
before the emergence of large models
it might be the entire internet industry
it for the product manager's abilities
a conceptual model of the brain has been outlined
So how should we interpret this table?
these numbers 012345, right
These numbers represent the demand intensity for this competency
the intensity of demand in different periods
or the horizontal axis
For example, this line represents time, right?
And then this number represents the intensity of demand
In other words, this table actually illustrates what we're discussing
Over time
As you progress in the role of a product manager
continuously delve deeper
So, what are the requirements for these abilities?
The higher the number
This means the higher the requirement for this skill.
Let's take another look at this table.
Let's add some supplementary information to look at this table.
Overall, I have categorized this table
On the horizontal axis, I have made some classifications
That is to say, if we look at it from an annual perspective
Overall, each of these columns may represent
how many years you have been working in this direction
Or, how many years you have been in the product manager position.
So this major categorization of competencies
Actually, it is broadly divided into four major directions.
What does each direction represent?
The first major area is called general competencies, right?
What does general ability represent
represents some inherent personal traits of yours
such as learning ability and execution ability
communication skills, etc.
Since it's a personal trait
What does it mean
This indicates that the matter does not vary significantly whether you are in school
or because you are working
it will undergo particularly significant changes
It's more about, well, you being a persistent
You yourself have strong execution skills
or you have strong learning abilities
Actually, regardless of what stage you're at
he is capable of making observations or demonstrating certain qualities
Therefore, these generic abilities
more emphasis is placed on what
more emphasis is placed on
When we enter the role of a product manager
or, for instance, if you've just graduated from school
or transition into a product manager role
we need to quickly adjust
our self-positioning in these general competencies
quickly adapt to the overall role of a product manager
What does a product manager actually need?
requires strong learning ability
strong execution capability
strong communication skills
It requires such a universal characteristic
So this is the first line, which is more related to personal traits.
The second line is called professional knowledge, right?
In the traditional perspective, professional knowledge
it includes both this technology
also includes project management knowledge, and so on, as well as possibly some others
For example, if it's a commercial product,
you may be required to master financial knowledge, right
or if you are more C-end oriented
more inclined towards this type of product design
is more focused on visual or interaction design
you may also need to master psychology, aesthetics, and more
These abilities, from a traditional perspective,
they all fall within the realm of what is called professional knowledge
then this category
We can actually see from the distribution of these numbers
It is actually a concept that leans towards linear growth.
So what does it require? It's on-demand learning plus linear accumulation.
Of course, this is professional knowledge from a traditional perspective, but AI is somewhat different.
So from a traditional perspective, product managers
So his expertise is actually, well
As you gradually delve deeper into the field
your professional knowledge
the mastery of professional knowledge in various directions
is a process of linear growth, and that's fine.
The second part is called professional skills
This professional skill
Actually, the core is the job skills of a product manager
Regarding this job skill, overall speaking
He has written a lot
Overall, it can be divided into two major categories
The first major category is called product execution capability
typically occurs within the first 0-3 years of a product manager's tenure
will be a core requirement
So what is product execution?
Product execution capability refers to how we take a product
a feature
bringing a module from scratch
from 0 to 1
from concept to entity, right
During this process, some aspects may be involved such as
for example, this might involve the entire production
the early stages of this execution
We may include things like market research
competitor research, right?
In the design phase
We may include elements such as flowcharts
PRD prototypes and other design drawings
Then in the product development phase
We may need to conduct reviews
to conduct this usability testing
and after the product is launched
may need to do some operations
or stages such as requirement feedback, etc.
During these stages
all the related capabilities
They are uniformly categorized as product execution capabilities.
because these are essentially about taking a product from 0 to 1
related to the core of making it happen
This is the first major component of a product manager's job skills
product execution
After working as a product manager for about 5 years,
We would consider that this product manager may have reached a relatively advanced stage
or advanced stage
Then after this stage
In addition to product execution
we will have one additional requirement
What is called business driving force
that we can drive this product
it makes money
Making money is just a very general concept
right, since we want to make money
That is, whose money to make
how to make money
how much money to make
Essentially, it's up to us to answer these questions.
In this process
we may involve some broader skills
For example, perhaps if you, say, you're working in B2B, right
you may need to look into abilities such as these, like business communication and commercial negotiation skills
if you are working in the ToC sector
you may need to focus more on marketing and operational skills
and so on and so forth
Whether you are in ToB or ToC, this kind of business drive
It is about achieving commercial value, right?
achieve market results and realize commercial value
This is the core, and this direction remains unchanged.
Therefore, we refer to the core competencies of a product manager
which are product execution and business drive, the two major components
Of course, the traditional perspective of the product competency model
also includes some organizational influence
These may then be
When you are in the role of a product manager
in the mid-to-late stages
our role shifts from frontline operations
gradually begin to transition into the role of a team manager
during the transition
We may need to acquire some additional skills
Now, returning to what we just mentioned, the core skills of a product manager
It runs through these competency segments.
the required experience and skills
Right, as I just mentioned
whether it's market research or design-related
various types of prototypes, flowcharts, etc.
including requirement reviews during development
progress management and other aspects
and also including the launch and operation
then the links involved in these aspects
it is actually the product manager
a concrete manifestation of his job skills
From the perspective of product manager job skills
we look at it and say
the product manager
it will form its own growth flywheel
Ah, this growth flywheel, the concept of the flywheel is what
spinning faster and faster, right
which means I can form my own closed loop
and then leverage my previous experiences to
to guide my current business
So, for product managers, many of the
Often, the path he takes is to analyze problems
design solutions, implement solutions, optimize solutions
It is through such cycles that continuous progress is made.
Of course, within this flywheel, there are some key components of its own.
The first key step is to analyze the problem, right
We need to be able to correctly analyze this business problem
that is through our own accumulated experiences
including some methodologies accumulated in our products
to position
what kind of problems currently exist in this scenario
Of course, the second point is
is to design and execute solutions
including optimization solutions
It is to solve business problems through reasonable solutions.
In other words
can we adopt some relatively standardized solutions
to solve a certain type of problem
Right, whether it's standardization or something else
a certain category
What is its essence actually
are all about abstracting these existing problems and their solutions
position them as a category of problems
Since it's a type of problem
then the next time a similar situation arises
we can consider saying hey
I actually have some accumulated standardized solutions now
So this is the product manager's
a path for their growth
OK so to briefly summarize
So the entire market has certain expectations for AI product managers
The first core demand is what
the job skills of a product manager
In other words, first and foremost, you must be a competent product manager.
Only then can you excel in the field of AI, right?
As we just mentioned, the AI product manager
In addition to being a product manager
it also involves AI
So what is the core of AI?
Actually, AI in this context
within this core competency
At its core, it represents the understanding and application of AI technologies
In other words, an AI product manager
Its work is essentially dancing on the edge of technological boundaries.
He is dancing on the edge of technology
What does that mean?
For example,
Suppose you are a product manager, right
Now, the requirement is that you need to design an online store
For example, we are a fresh produce e-commerce platform
design one in that mini-program, or some kind of APP
Our first instinct might be to say OK
how should I design
the presentation of Me products, right
how to arrange the product images
how to place the description below
to provide users with the best visual experience
Then, after the product is displayed
probably need to add to cart, right?
After adding to cart, generate an order
After generating the order, proceed to payment.
This is actually what we need to design, some of the more core mainstream processes.
core main process
Of course, there may also be some more advanced
You might think, OK, does my payment allow refunds?
may need to support refund functionality
Or should I now issue some
a 20 off for every 100 coupon
I need to support coupon functionality, and so on and so forth.
At this moment, as a product manager
when seeing the concepts of online mall
the first thing that pops into our minds
The first thing that comes to mind
We tend to focus more on this
What is the process of this matter?
Right, the concrete manifestations of this matter
Let's talk about some concrete examples
So in this process,
Few product managers would consider whether
Is this thing I designed technically feasible?
Can the technology achieve it?
Few would have this line of thinking
Why
The reason is, in e-commerce and other
these relatively mature scenarios
Technology is actually in a state of overflow
What does it mean to be in an overflow state
That is to say, the technology may be able to address 95%
even 98% of the problems
Of course, the technology we're referring to here is the overall development of the industry's technology.
right
It's not about any individual
an individual cannot solve a certain type of problem
That might be an issue with individual competence.
We say the entire industry
its technology is actually in a state of overall overflow
in other words
What does overflow mean?
as long as you're not dealing with something like 618
events like Double 11, which need to withstand tens of millions
or even hundreds of millions of people shopping simultaneously
Currently, the development of technology is sufficient for the vast majority of cases.
So in many cases, when designing products,
We won't over-consider technical feasibility
Meanwhile, for the success or failure of an online store
the decision, or rather its decisive factor
nor is it technology, right
This is our perspective on some traditional internet scenarios
or within product operations,
This is a core consideration in the mindset of a product manager.
But if you were to shift this to the AI industry
For example, how would you design an AI-powered virtual try-on product
Right, after I take a photo,
Hey, my clothes can switch automatically
and it fits perfectly
Then what should you consider
Your first reaction may not be
first consider the issue of the process
Your first reaction should be to say OK
the current AI technology
Can it distinguish between my top and bottom
Can it distinguish between people and clothing?
Right, and also okay, now after the clothing is switched
This is because it is it
You may have different poses, right?
For example, when you raise your hands or place them on your hips
Your clothes cannot have a fixed shape.
then I replace it with the new clothes
Can it also change according to the person's posture?
These issues may not yet be related to the process or anything else
What we need to consider first is whether this is feasible.
What we need to verify first is the feasibility of this approach or feature.
So what is the feasibility of this idea or feature in essence?
Essentially, it's about first verifying whether this technology is feasible.
Therefore, AI technology is for the AI industry
Its uniqueness lies in the fact that the current AI industry or AI products
its core driving force and its core boundaries
are all along the line of technology
Right, for example, your online mall
the success or failure of an online mall
you can't say it's due to technical influence
It might be his supply source
It might be the quality of the product.
It could also be the user base of his product
or it could be the scale of his e-commerce user base, right
whether the operations are well-executed
the size of the discount
All these factors will affect its success or failure
But currently, for AI products,
The quality of the technology or the boundaries of the overall technological trends
it will actually have a comprehensive impact on an AI product's cost
So for an AI product manager
why do we call it dancing on the edge of technology
Because you need to deeply understand the boundaries of AI technology
you can then understand, what level we can roughly achieve
This is the impact of AI technology on the AI industry
It has a unique impact.
So why do we need AI, PM, which stands for AI Product Manager
Why is it necessary to master this technical understanding?
What is its actual value
Because what we're doing more now is
transform some AI technologies through a productization path
and then deliver value to the users, right
The deeper your understanding of the technology
Or the more comprehensive your understanding of the technology is
it will reduce your efforts in translating technology into products
this intermediate path
especially reducing such communication costs
For example, technology actually plays a significant role in various aspects
It plays a strong role at every stage
For example, in the requirements phase, right
we can accurately assess whether this idea, well,
I have an idea
a new direction
a new idea that users might also need
but I don't know if it's technically feasible
If you have technical understanding
then you can make a relatively accurate assessment
whether this technology is feasible, right
For example, in such voice assistants
Can we accurately identify
the distinction between phonetic text and semantic meaning
Right? What is this aspect of sound
For example, there might be some background noise, right?
Or this person, their timbre is different from others.
Semantics, it emphasizes more on what the content of the speech is.
regardless of who said it
There might be some coupling between them, right?
Then, for example, during the development phase
we can communicate more with the algorithm team to ensure smooth collaboration
for many traditional
such internet product scenarios
In fact, many teams often do not
Will they allocate resources to algorithm or strategy direction?
Only a few specific areas
such as e-commerce or advertising
will only set up such a search team
Many products only have engineering teams.
So, one characteristic of AI products is
there must be a large number of algorithmic engineers present
So if we can master this technology
have a certain understanding of technology
we can achieve better alignment with the algorithms, right
For example, I can communicate various requirements with him
or define various metrics
Then in the operational phase
our insights
is about the insight into data anomalies
Moreover, as the understanding of technology improves
will also lead to better judgment
For example, this online data, right
constantly fluctuating
this for example, the success rate of my tasks
or task accuracy rate
may fluctuate continuously
Then during our analysis,
If it's this relatively traditional approach
we may only look at OK
Ok
This could be due to changes in user behavior or functional stability.
So with this technical understanding,
We will also understand that OK
Me model, in fact, its performance itself is also fluctuating
Right, the performance of the model can also degrade, and so on.
In this way, our analytical perspective will become more comprehensive.
Of course, this also includes aspects like long-term iterations, right?
How can we improve our product?
That is to say, we can develop this confusion matrix
right, to look at metrics like accuracy
recall rate
and other key indicators to analyze
how to optimize the product more comprehensively
So when a person, when an AI product manager
his understanding of the technology is sufficient
then he can make the entire product lifecycle
can make the entire process smoother
smoother
This is actually a very, very important point.
On the other hand
technical comprehension
It is essentially a line of defense for controlling product risks, right?
For example, what does it mean to control the product's defense line
that is to say, if a person, if an HPM
If an AHPM
He lacks technical understanding
if he doesn't have a thorough understanding of the technology
then the consequences would be extremely dire
For example, this might lead to the emergence of such pseudo-demands, right?
What is a pseudo-demand
For example, the most classic pseudo-demand is
I want a phone case that can emit fragrances
This is actually a very typical case of neglecting technical feasibility.
forcefully proposing such demands
For example, the case I'm citing now
saying that a certain intelligent customer manager proposed, right
I need to be able to identify 100% of users' complaint intentions
But in fact, the current technical boundaries we have
The recognition rate is 90%.
then the remaining percentage will inevitably include some misidentifications
If on this basis
we don't implement any of this, we don't design any fallback mechanisms
without any such other measures, like bypasses
I'll handle the contingency in case of misidentification
what should be done
such product design
That would lead to, well,
I believe this step is absolutely 100%
Right, in terms of product design, it's 100%.
I just go with 100%
then you have no alternative routes
will lead to a large number of misjudgments
then you will trigger more customer complaints
This may also include, for example, resource misallocation
whether the product can truly grasp
What is the most critical thing to optimize at present
and what roughly is the path to this optimization
For example, many of our AI products
It will have the concept of accuracy rate
Should it be optimized within the product
or optimize outside the product
it is often a problem
Right, internal product optimization means okay, I'll predict I'll optimize
is my product's own strategy
including Me prompt
Me's process mechanism, right, and
Should I add some assistance during the process
Additionally, optimizations can be made outside the product
for example, the selection of my base model
a certain technical model
It is relatively weak in terms of its coding capabilities.
It excels in image processing capabilities
then our selection of this technical model
Is it the most optimal logic
Or is there going to be an updated version of the model
It's about these accuracy rates where I don't need to do anything
as the capabilities of the foundational model improve
This accuracy rate improves on its own.
without requiring any additional effort from me
This actually affects product managers' judgment on the priority of many current matters
its priority assessment
If you lack this technical understanding
you might demand, hey, don't think about anything else
Just do it ourselves anyway
optimize the 2% accuracy rate
Then this may not be the most economical
the most cost-effective solution
This is the risk of resource misallocation.
Of course, AI products also have a significant problem
that is, ethical out-of-control
Nowadays, many people are using AI products to do this
We are currently designing many AI products
especially AI-generated products, right
whether you're generating text or images
or generate audio and video
then ethics is actually a
AI ethics is a very important direction
then for the content generated by the model
Actually, effective review and alignment need to be implemented, right?
For example, if the product is designing this process chain
He didn't consider that okay
I am, I am generating images, right
conduct some review and alignment
That may lead some users to exploit the text-to-image service I provide
image generation product to produce some content, such as pornography, violence, or terrorism-related materials, etc.
things like involving violence or social anxiety
Although large models inherently possess such capabilities
but may not be able to block, so in many cases
When we design products,
keep this in mind
that is the issue of ethical out-of-control
Essentially, it also arises from some fundamental principles.
So overall it appears that
With technical understanding
you can actually streamline the entire product lifecycle
Right, if there's a lack of technical understanding,
then many risks may arise
So overall, this understanding of AI technology
It is actually a very important capability for an IPM.
Why is that the case?
Because in fact, for AI product managers, in many cases
its core value lies in what
within the existing technological boundaries
We achieve this through productization, right? For example,
can be achieved through various designs
manage user expectations
to quickly achieve PMF
What is PMF
It means that my product matches the market demand.
called called called PMF
Only when PMF is achieved
only then can it be said
your product will generate its corresponding economic value
So when we look at PMF, it's actually a bidirectional process, right?
you need to have both product and market
Then again, the product
It is actually a boundary strongly influenced by technology.
Therefore, in this scenario
First and foremost, we need to strongly understand
Where exactly is the current technological boundary?
for example
For example, the current technical boundary is at an 80-AI level
is at an 80-point level
but the users we need to face
it may be a distribution that is relatively
their expectations of your AI are widely distributed
Some people may have expectations of you as high as 120 points
Right, there's an extremely high expectation
He believes that AI should be omnipotent.
Some people, due to their past experiences
He may not have used AI very well or effectively in the past.
His expectation of you is only 40 points.
He thinks you're just an AI, right?
You don't have stable output either
your output capability is also unstable
and sometimes your results are wrong
and some relatively simple math problems
You might still get it wrong, and so on, I mean you
We work as AI product managers
we often face
its user expectations are highly divergent
In this context
The core value of an AI product manager lies in
First, you need to understand why the current AI technology
It's at an 80-point level
This 80-point score, for example, if the full score is 100,
the missing 20 points
where are the roughly missing points located
So what does this 80-point level actually mean for us
Which product capabilities are limited
Or one day when this 80-point level becomes 85 points
which of my product capabilities will be enhanced
This is the product
from the perspective of an AI product manager
He is on the product or technology side, trying to achieve understanding
Similarly, another perspective he looks at is this market
facing this, this group's expectations of AI range from 40 to 120 points
a user group
So what is the core capability he needs to develop
He needs to influence these users' expectations
It needs to employ some productization methods
make users gradually realize
the current technology is at an 80-point level
Certainly, some excellent product design
It might be able to raise the 80 to 82 or 83
just to make users feel that, okay, this product seems pretty impressive
but fundamentally speaking
We are targeting users ranging from 40 to 120 points
guide to the 80-point level
this fluctuating state
What are some productization methods
For example, for users with very high expectations
we may provide more of what
provide some pre-guidance
the logic of some verbal strategies
Right? Like you're asking me many questions beyond my capability boundary
I will tactfully guide you
guide it to the range of problems I can solve
So for those who distrust our AI
or users with low expectations of AI capabilities
What should I enhance for them
Boost his confidence how
boost confidence
Make myself transparent to boost his confidence
What if I tell you how I think
right, expose my chain of thought
Or, let me provide you with a large amount of indexed content from Me
You see, my content isn't just made up.
It's not generated by my hallucinations
I am all based on his existing Knowledge
or summarize from existing web links
to enhance the information for these low-expectation users
These are actually some commonly used, productized methods.
So as an AI product manager
On one hand, we look at the current technical boundaries
one side looks at how to manage user expectations
and then bring the two ends as close as possible
to achieve a PMF
During this process
It is one of the most classic or core foundational
underlying premise
That is, we need to maintain an understanding and application of AI technologies.
So here, let's address one more issue
Many, in fact, those who aspire to become AI product managers
this student
there might be an issue
I often hear many people asking this question
Well, you know, it's about AI products
What kind of technical skills does it actually require, right?
This issue also has another expression
whether product managers should write code
This question is almost frequently asked
Well, here, let me share one of my understandings.
That is to say, should product managers learn to code, right?
Essentially, it's what we often refer to as technical capability
In fact, technical capabilities can be divided into two perspectives
one is called technical execution
one is called technical understanding
Both of them fall under the scope of technical capabilities.
So for product managers
What we need more is technical comprehension, right?
What is technical execution?
Technical execution capability refers to being given an objective
Can you achieve it through the means of coding
execute this goal
For example, asking you to write a small game like Snake
You may need to use a programming language you're familiar with
For example, you know Java
can write Python, can write C++, etc.
then successfully write it out in this way
run successfully
This is called technical execution.
Of course, the problems you face may become increasingly complex
Right, do you have the ability to, well, get it done and execute this task properly?
So what does technical comprehension mean
Technical comprehension emphasizes that I may or may not
I may not be able to write code, right or
I don't actually require
I need to do it by writing code
What I mean is that I can comprehend some complex technical concepts.
I can understand the logic behind how some technologies operate
perhaps not from the perspective of code
But I can turn it into something, something I can understand, right?
I can roughly understand what the steps are like.
This is called technical comprehension.
So why do we need to break down technical capabilities into execution power and comprehension?
Because an AI product manager
what we actually emphasize as the core
or essentially focus on technical comprehension
Right, product managers don't need to have strong technical execution skills
you don't actually need to write code
Of course, being able to write code is a good thing.
Then why do we say the opposite
Perhaps learning a bit of coding wouldn't do you any harm.
This is because, for many people, the way they grasp technical understanding
In fact, they first mastered the execution of technology
he gradually acquired technical understanding
Of course, we do not deny that some people
his thinking ability
strong logical ability, right
or have a strong foundation in mathematics
He can directly bypass the stage of execution
Well
to directly gain an understanding of the technology
Of course, that is also a very good approach
However, most people
their path is to first develop execution capabilities
In other words, you first need to learn a certain type of code
Then, you can grasp some understanding of this technology.
Well, that approach is also acceptable.
So, should product managers write code?
you can refer to the concept mentioned earlier
to drive forward
Let me elaborate a bit more here
What exactly does the concretization in technical understanding refer to?
So I believe technical understanding can roughly be divided into four stages
that is, our understanding of technology
We can also use this method to evaluate
Which level are we at?
The first level of technical comprehension is called single-point understanding
What is single-point understanding
Let me explain a technical concept to you today
For example, large models, their their core
Its core model is called Transformer
How does it work
You understand, OK? This is the first layer.
called single-point comprehension
The second is called conceptual abstraction
Right? What is conceptual abstraction
So today I listened to this model
listened to that model again tomorrow
Then I feel that these two models
They only differ superficially and in parameters, right?
or these two implementation approaches
However, the overarching concept they abstract is
are all about gradually simplifying a problem
to make it easier for the next model to handle.
You can understand at this level
What does that mean
you have some concepts
You have abstracted some individual concepts
This is the second level of technical comprehension.
What is the third level
The third level is about you being able to establish a knowledge system
What is a knowledge system?
That is to say, OK, I not only understand individual points of the problem
I also know them, and can abstract them to a higher level
So what does the knowledge system emphasize?
It emphasizes that in your mind, a directory may gradually emerge, ah,
This directory represents this direction, right
How does its evolution process unfold
What are its branches
or this scenario
What solutions do I have to solve its problem?
Then, a directory like this will gradually form in your mind.
Then this directory
It gradually forms a technical knowledge system.
This is the third-level requirement
So we say the highest level of technical comprehension is
What is metaphorical communication
As we often say, it's called making the difficult look easy.
right, or in other words, to simplify the complex
Because as an AI product manager
Many times, we grasp the essence of the technology
is actually about communicating technology
So if your level can reach the point where you can say OK
Ok
I can explain a complex technical concept
to a non-technical person
can also explain it clearly and understandably
So in fact, this level of technical comprehension
is equivalent to reaching the highest level
This is also a level that PMs, many AI PMs, should strive to achieve.
Because in many cases, what we're actually doing for users
whether you are in the C-end or B-end
What you do for the users is precisely this matter
to translate a complex technical concept
help users understand through certain methods
especially now
especially in the B2B sector
Many scenarios are like this.
So if you can achieve, hey
I can also give some vivid analogies
For example, we take the training of large models
If you can come up with metaphorical approaches
make it easier for non-technical people to understand
then your technical comprehension and communication skills
in fact, it's akin to reaching a state of true mastery
So we say everyone can refer to these four levels, right
to continuously enhance our technical comprehension
its state
Okay, so this is the second line
That is the understanding and application of AI technology.
Let's take another look at the market's expectations for AIPM
There is also a third demand line in its core competencies
That's what we call the accumulation and insight of business scenarios.
So what exactly are business scenarios? Identifying the entry points for AI in business scenarios is crucial.
In other words
business scenarios
In fact, it's about identifying where we can integrate AI into these areas
or in which scenarios to leverage the value of AI
So what is a business scenario
In fact, when we look at how the country defines it
This is when the nation is promoting its AI strategy
We often hear about things like AI plus finance, right?
AI plus healthcare, etc.
the concept behind this 'AI plus'
This is what we commonly refer to as the business scenario.
For example,
Let's take AI in healthcare as an example, right
What is the concrete business scenario?
That is, a patient, if they go to the hospital for medical treatment
What exactly does this process look like
For example, if someone falls ill, right
What he needs to do might be to first register
After registration, go to the hospital for triage
After triage
to find the corresponding doctor
Then go to different departments for examinations
Finally, all the examination results are compiled and handed over to the doctor.
The doctor makes a judgment based on the examination results
issue the prescription for diagnosis
and then develop a treatment plan, right
whether it's injections or medications
this process
In fact, it describes a specific business scenario within the healthcare domain.
So, if you want to work in the healthcare direction
become an AI product manager
medical AI product manager
If you don't understand this direction
then it's very difficult for you
You don't understand these business processes or scenarios mentioned earlier
then it's very difficult for you to come up with something like OK
I want to reduce the cost for doctors during consultations
or I want to enhance the communication experience for patients during consultations
patient experience
Even if you have a strong understanding of technology
You lack some business insights
you will also find it very difficult to achieve this
So what does the business scenario primarily provide us with?
it's about identifying the right scenarios for AI to step in
what value to provide to users
solve what kind of problems
So how do we accumulate these business scenarios, or in other words,
How do we gain insights into these business scenarios?
Essentially, there are these few perspectives, right?
Let's take the previous example again
For example, if we want to examine the medical field
the business scenario
I need to gain insights into it
First of all, it's actually a process of moving from the macro to the micro perspective.
First, what is the market trend, right?
the entire large healthcare industry
What is its perception of AI?
What is the level of awareness of AI in this context?
Then the second step, what is the business process
as I just mentioned
Then the patient starts from registration
until he finally receives the diagnosis and treatment
the process during this period
We need to first sort it out
Then the third step is, what are the pain points?
Right, that is to say, what are the patients experiencing during this process
what are the pain points
For example, the patient may need to visit multiple departments.
The patient may have to carry a bunch of
the test results he can't understand
Right, or the patient may also lack some
in the process of seeking medical treatment
he may have to run around
Or they may not understand why these tests are necessary.
These processes are essentially the pain points along the patient's journey.
As for the pain points of doctors
Perhaps it means that doctors have to face a large number of patients every day.
there are a large number of documentation work records, right
These are equivalent to some medical diagnostic records.
This is a large amount of paperwork.
It is possible that he has to spend a lot of time
explaining to patients, which is largely about alleviating their concerns
or explaining the workflow
He may spend a lot of time and so on.
These are all the pain points that exist in this business.
Of course, it's not that this business
This business is not to say that all the pain points of the business itself
all can be resolved by AI
Therefore, we should next examine in conjunction with AI's own capabilities
what AI can do in this process
and how AI could potentially intervene in this process
Is it perceptible to users
users' perception of the logic behind AI intervention
or what is their level of acceptance
For example, if we let AI completely replace the doctor
to diagnose users
That might be the case for many patients
his psychological acceptance level is relatively low
it's not quite acceptable, right
then we may need to shift to an auxiliary diagnostic logic
Ah, wait
These are actually all within the business scenarios we encounter
the things it needs to accumulate and gain insights into
Okay, let's recap.
Right, as we just mentioned about AI product managers
there are three major core competency models
the job skills of a product manager
the understanding and application of AI technology, as well as the accumulation and insight of business scenarios
So understanding these core competency models
What exactly is the role of this for us?
First and foremost, it can greatly enhance our understanding
help us understand that
What are the positioning and expectations of AI for talents?
What does this mean
For example, let's look at these three lines we just mentioned, right?
We actually find that in the current market, its positioning for AI,
Its positioning for AIPM is actually a highly interdisciplinary
a highly comprehensive positioning
That is to say, you need to understand both product
understand technology
and understand the business
then in reality the market may have very few people who can simultaneously excel in all three areas
very few people meet these three criteria
In other words
if any
then it is also very expensive
So perhaps the entire market has certain expectations for AI Product Managers
its core requirements
First, we can understand that it is
It is highly interdisciplinary
the requirements are highly comprehensive
At the same time, because such versatile talent
they actually exist, but in relatively small numbers
So many companies can actually accept that
OK you're not strong in all three areas right
you have one or two lines
that you have some lines where you may not be as experienced
that's OK
because we are currently in a phase of market transformation
and this stage of demand explosion
that is to say, you may not be fully equipped
you can also take on this task
So this provides a reference for our career transition
provides a reference for job hunting and career transition
In other words
everyone who wants to pursue a career as an AI product manager
such a candidate
they can evaluate themselves based on these three dimensions
What kind of persona do I have in the overall market
What kind of professional persona do I have in the job market?
Am I a product manager with a basic understanding of technology
or a technical expert with some business knowledge
or a business expert with some product knowledge
Right, we can assess ourselves based on our distribution and accumulation along these three dimensions.
this distribution
is the accumulation and distribution situation, to
have a reasonable assessment of oneself
that is, how exactly should I go about transitioning
becoming an AI product manager
At the same time, if you are already an AI product manager, or, right,
But these three lines will also help you develop a better long-term
self-improvement path
These three lines will continue to play a role in the subsequent process
continuously play a role in our careers
play a long-term promoting role
so understanding this core competency model
It actually serves both our job-seeking and career growth
This is a very crucial matter.
Finally, let's briefly take a look at what makes a good AI product manager
What is his growth path
Initially, it's about the introduction to thinking skills and tools, right
and possess the basic execution skills of a product manager
Then in the process of evolution
For example, possibly in the early stages, right
1 to 2 years
We continuously strengthen our product thinking and technical awareness.
as well as from 0 to 1
from 1 to n, right
whether for new products or the iteration of mature product modules
have mastered a wealth of these experiences
Finally, in the continuous practice of product development
to accumulate our business perspectives
and then integrate our core competencies in various aspects
achieve long-term improvement
Alright, that's all the content we have for today.
The Core Competency Model of AI Product Managers
Okay, thank you everyone